Guide to the Cuban Revolution Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Andrew St. George Photographs, Films, and Papers, 1957-1960; Series I
  - Photographs
    - Contact Book VIII
      - Book VIII Print 73: Congress of the Federación Nacional de Trabajadores del Azucar in Havana, 1959 December (Box 6, Folder 632)
        Congress of the Federación Nacional de Trabajadores del Azucar [FNTA], representing 234 sugar workers' unions, held in Havana in mid-December 1959. In attendance at the front table on stage are Conrado Becquer, the head of the FNTA (smoking a cigar), Prime Minister Fidel Castro and President Osvaldo Dorticós. David Salvador, President of the CTC, the FNTA's umbrella union, is pictured giving a speech. Although affiliated to the 26th of July Movement from the beginning of the Revolution, Salvador eventually resigned from the directorship of the union in April of 1960 and was subsequently convicted of counterrevolutionary activities for which he received a twenty-year prison sentence. See also Prints 75, 79, 80, 83, 84, 85 and 86.
      - Book VIII Print 74: Havana airport and travelers; balcony of unidentified hotel, 1959 December (Box 6, Folder 633)
        Flight of the unidentified foreigner pictured boarding an airplane in Havana in Print 75. Also includes images of airport waiting room at the airport in Havana, showing Fidel Castro on a television screen, as well as pictures taken from a balcony of a hotel in a unidentified location. See also Print 75.
      - Book VIII Print 75: Congress of the Federación Nacional de Trabajadores del Azucar; travelers boarding flight at Havana airport, 1959 December (Box 6, Folder 634)
        Congress of the Federación Nacional de Trabajadores del Azucar [FNTA], representing 234 sugar workers' unions, held in Havana in mid-December 1959. Pictured speaking before the microphones and cameras is the Secretary General of the CTC, David Salvador. Seated beside Fidel Castro is Osvaldo Dorticós on his left and Conrado Becquer, head of the FNTA, on his right. Other frames show an unidentified foreign man and his wife as they board a flight from Havana's airport in the company of the photographer. See also Prints 73, 79, 80, 83, 84, 85, 86; for images of the flight of the unidentified foreigner, see Print 74.
      - Book VIII Print 76: Images of an unidentified elegantly dressed woman standing in what appears to be the second-floor lobby balcony of the Havana Hilton. Other images show the interior courtyard of the hotel. See also Prints 71 and 72., 1960 (Box 6, Folder 635)
      - Book VIII Print 77: Fidel Castro in an unidentified location appears to be meeting with a group of foreigners and press agents, [1959-1960] (Box 6, Folder 636)
      - Book VIII Print 78: Interior courtyard of the Havana Hilton; men at Restaurante El Polinesio and Restaurant La Zaragozana, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 637)
        Top row of frames shows the interior courtyard of the Havana Hilton. Second row and fifth row of frames show an unidentified foreign man wearing a business suit as he greets two Cuban men also wearing suits, one of whom wears glasses, at the Restaurante El Polinesio located on a wing of the Habana Hilton. These men accompany him outside the hotel to the taxi stand where they are seen talking. The fourth row of frames (32-37) shows the unidentified man at the Restaurant La Zaragozana with the man wearing glasses. See Prints 39, 81, 82, and 86.
      - Book VIII Print 79: Fidel Castro addresses delegates and the media at the Congress of the Federación Nacional de Trabajadores del Azucar [FNTA], representing 234 sugar workers' unions, held in Havana. See also Prints 73, 75, 80, 83, 84, 85 and 86., 1959 December (Box 6, Folder 638)
      - Book VIII Print 80: Fidel Castro addresses delegates and the media at the Congress of the Federación Nacional de Trabajadores del Azucar; militiamen searching an unidentified man, 1959 December (Box 6, Folder 639)
        Fidel Castro addresses delegates and the media at the Congress of the Federación Nacional de Trabajadores del Azucar [FNTA], representing 234 sugar workers' unions, held in Havana in mid-December 1959. Other frames show a militiaman (wearing a beret) in the act of frisking and searching an unidentified man while another man pointing a pistol looks on. These events seem to have taken place in a bathroom, possibly in a private residence where Fidel Castro was at the time (such as that of Celia Sánchez, pictured in Prints 58, 60, and 64). See also Prints 73, 75, 83, 84, 85 and 86.
      - Book VIII Print 81: Man at the Polynesian restaurant in the Havana Hilton Hotel; leading women activists speaking for television broadcast, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 640)
        Top frames depict an unidentified foreign man wearing a business suit speaking on the telephone and posing for the photographer's camera at the Polynesian restaurant at the Havana Hilton Hotel. The second set of frames shows images of a bathroom followed by images of the same man greeting a Cuban with glasses and wearing a tie and jacket at the Polynesian restaurant. The last two sets of frames show a panel of leading women activists of the period, apparently speaking for a television broadcast. Frames 28 and 29 show from left to right, Loló de la Torriente, Vilma Espín, E. Lina Milanés and an unidentified older woman with white hair and glasses. For images of the unidentified foreigner and his Cuban counterparts see also Prints 39, 79, 82, and 86. For other images of the female panelists, see Prints 66 and 67.
      - Book VIII Print 82: Images of an unidentified foreign man wearing a business suit as he types a multi-page document on a typewriter. The same man is also shown at another point in the day as he has a dinner meeting at the Restaurant La Zaragozana in Old Havana. See also Prints 39, 79, 81, 82 and 86., 1960 (Box 6, Folder 641)
      - Book VIII Print 83: Fidel Castro addresses delegates and the media at the Congress of the Federación Nacional de Trabajadores del Azucar [FNTA], representing 234 sugar workers' unions, held in Havana. See also Prints 73, 75, 84, 85 and 86., 1959 December (Box 6, Folder 642)
      - Book VIII Print 84: Secretary General of the CTC, David Salvador, addresses delegates and the media at the Congress of the Federación Nacional de Trabajadores del Azucar, 1959 December (Box 6, Folder 643)
        Secretary General of the CTC, David Salvador, addresses delegates and the media at the Congress of the Federación Nacional de Trabajadores del Azucar [FNTA], representing 234 sugar workers' unions, held in Havana in mid-December 1959. Other frames show the workers' delegates' enthusiastic response to Salvador's speech and reporters crowding around Fidel Castro as he smiles and holds up a package wrapped in twine. See also Prints 73, 75, 83, 85 and 86.
      - Book VIII Print 85: Fidel Castro addresses delegates and the media at the Congress of the Federación Nacional de Trabajadores del Azucar [FNTA], representing 234 sugar workers' unions, held in Havana. See also Prints 73, 75, 83, 84 and 86, 1959 December (Box 6, Folder 644)
      - Book VIII Print 86: Fidel Castro giving speech on "Ante la Prensa"; foreigner dining at La Zaragozana; Fidel Castro addressing delegates at the Federación Nacional de Trabajadores del Azucar, 1959 December (Box 6, Folder 645)
        Top row of frames shows Fidel Castro giving a speech on Cuba's national television program, "Ante la Prensa," in which he holds up a newspaper clipping featuring two articles: one on new state regulations on the number of hours that employees could work in the business sector during the Christmas season, the other titled, "Actuaba el Padre Aguirre de Batabanó en contra la Revolución (Father Aguirre of Batabanó acted against the Revolution"). Second row of frames shows an unidentified foreigner dining at La Zaragozana, a restaurant near the Parque Central of Havana. Bottom rows of frames show Fidel Castro addressing delegates and the media at the Congress of the Federación Nacional de Trabajadores del Azucar [FNTA], representing 234 sugar workers' unions, held in Havana. For images of the FNTA congress and Fidel speaking on television, see also Prints 73, 75, 83, 84 and 85; for images of the unidentified foreigner, see also Prints 78, 81 and 82.
      - Book VIII Print 87: Fidel Castro giving speech on "Ante la Prensa." See also Print 86., 1959 December (Box 6, Folder 646)
    - Contact Book IX
      - St. George descriptions (Box 7, Folder 647)
      - Book IX Print 1: Fidel Castro addresses the nation in televised address before Cuban flag, probably in honor of February 24, 1960, anniversary of the 1895 Grito de Baire. Contains smaller print taken from same contact sheet (Box 7, Folder 648)
      - Book IX Print 2: Gathering at stage where Fidel Castro is one of the speakers, 1960 June (Box 7, Folder 649)
        Public gathering before a stage where Fidel is one of the speakers. This event appears to have been held on the far-end of the Malecón, or the sea wall skirting the entrance to the Bay of Havana. It was one of many public rallies held to celebrate the Cuban government's campaign to nationalize increasing numbers of U.S.-owned businesses following conflict over Cuba's decision to accept the Soviet Union's offer to sell unrefined oil to Cuba at much reduced prices in May of 1960. The resulting confrontation with the U.S. government led to the nationalization of U.S. oil refineries in Cuba and sparked the process of general nationalization and confiscation which this rally celebrates. See also Print 3.
      - Book IX Print 3: Public protest against Cuban Republic, 1960 June (Box 7, Folder 650)
        Public protest on the Malecón (Sea Wall) of Havana at which a bonfire is made of a tall wooden effigy representing the Cuban Republic. Small images depict corrupt politicians, the cultural decadence of the period and a black coffin with the face of a skeleton refers to cycles of state terror and violence against Cuban citizens. The effigy is being shown as it is torched and later as it burns before a sizeable crowd of thousands. This rally was one of many public demonstrations held in the summer and fall of 1960 in order to celebrate the Cuban government's decision to nationalize U.S.-owned businesses and properties in Cuba. See also Print 1.
      - Book IX Print 4: Newspaper office (?), 1960 (Box 7, Folder 651)
        Images of an unidentified man examining a newspaper on a podium-style desk with a large salon in the background. This salon, staffed by a large number of writers sitting at desks with typewriters, appears to show a large newspaper office, for its size, possibly Diario de la Marina, which was housed in a large building on Prado, directly facing the Capitolio. This was the first national newspaper to be occupied by militias loyal to the government and nationalized for supporting counterrevolutionary activities in May of 1960. See also Print 9 and Contact Book 10.
      - Book IX Print 5: Carlos Rafael Rodriguez being interviewed on "Ante la Prensa," Cuba's version of "Meet the Press,", 1960 June (Box 7, Folder 652)
        View from catwalk of television studio of the show "Ante la Prensa," Cuba's version of "Meet the Press," on which government officials, especially Fidel Castro, made regular appearances. On this occasion, the main official being interviewed is Carlos Rafael Rodríguez, a member of the historic Communist Party in Cuba, called until 1961, the Partido Socialista Popular (PSP) and important journalist in Cienfuegos, Cuba. Rodríguez was appointed to join Prime Minister Fidel Castro's governing cabinet and as the radicalization of the Revolution proceeded in 1960, was increasingly given a much higher-profile role, despite his long-time affiliation with the PSP. Such an affiliation, prior to 1960, was considered a liability for the Castro-led government. See also Prints 7 and 9.
      - Book IX Print 6: Raúl Castro giving speech on national television; women militias, 1960 June (Box 7, Folder 653)
        Bottom frames of the sheet show Raúl Castro, the Chief of Cuba's Fuerzas Armadas Revolucionarias from October 1959 to the present, giving a speech on national television. Top half of the images show members of the Unidad Femenina Revolucionaria training at the parade grounds of El Morro Fortress, as well as another group of women dressed in civilian clothes being taught how to march by officers of the Fuerzas Armadas. These first militias were trained and organized in November and December, 1959. The pictures are probably taken early in the winter of 1960 when the photographer visited Cuba for a lengthy stay. Also present is a reporter from California where shots of the same uniformed women subsequently appeared in newspapers owned by C.K. McClatchy, the Sacramento Bee, the Modesto Bee and the Fresno Bee. See also Prints 6, 7, and 8.
      - Book IX Print 7: Unidad Femenina Revolucionaria shown training; Carlos Rafael Rodríguez's televised appearance on the program "Ante la Prensa,", 1960 June (Box 7, Folder 654)
        Unidad Femenina Revolucionaria, one of Cuba's first all-female militias, organized in the closing months of 1959 and shown training on the parade grounds of Havana's El Morro Fortress, facing the Bay of Havana. Some of the images are double-exposed with shots of the arrival of an aircraft at Havana's international airport. The upper half of the sheet contains images of Carlos Rafael Rodríguez's televised appearance on the program "Ante la Prensa." See also Prints 5, 6, 8 and 9.
      - Book IX Print 8: Raúl Castro, the Chief of Cuba's Fuerzas Armadas Revolucionarias from October 1959 to the present, giving a speech on national television. See also Prints 6 and 18., 1960 (Box 7, Folder 655)
      - Book IX Print 9: The top two rows of frames show the same unidentified man, probably a journalist or editor, as documented in Print 4. Bottom rows offer images of Carlos Rafael Rodríguez appearing on the national television program "Ante la Prensa." See also Prints 4, 5 and 7., 1960 June (Box 7, Folder 656)
      - Book IX Print 10: National congress of the Confederación de Trabajadores Cubanos, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 657)
        Images of the national congress of the Confederación de Trabajadores Cubanos [CTC], Cuba's largest labor union, held in November of 1959. Frames in the top four rows and bottom row of the sheet show Fidel Castro sitting at the front table on stage with Efigenio Ameijeiras to his right, Osmani Cienfuegos standing above Fidel and speaking in his ear, and David Salvador, Secretary General of the CTC until April of 1960 when his criticism of policies centralizing state control over unions led to his expulsion, initially on charges of corruption that later changed to accusations of counterrevolution. The man speaking before the microphone is an unidentified labor delegate. Frame 25 of the bottom row shows Violeta Casals, a famous radio-novela actress who lent her voice to the clandestine radio station known as Radio Rebelde during the war against Batista in the late 1950s. See also Contact Book 10.
      - Book IX Prints 11-16: Swimming pool at the Hotel Presidente; monument to Tomás Estrada Palma, 1960 June (Box 7, Folder 658-663)
        Photographs of tourists cavorting at the swimming pool of the Hotel Presidente, located on the Avenida de los Presidentes (also known as "G" Street) in el Vedado, Havana, across the street from what is today Cuba's Ministerio de Relaciones Exteriores (MINREX), a banker's former home. Prints 15 and 16 clearly show the monument to Tomás Estrada Palma on the street in front of the pool area of the hotel. Estrada Palma was Cuba's first President, installed in an uncontested election in 1902, held during the first U.S. military occupation of Cuba (1898-1902). This is significant because all monuments to republican-era political figures were desecrated by government order in early 1961. Today, only the pedestal still stands, topped by the statue of Tomás Estrada Palma's bronze shoes, which workers were not able to remove from the base of the pedestal. See also Prints 17 and 35.
      - Book IX Print 17: Fidel Castro arriving at Havana airport; tourists at swimming pool at the Hotel Presidente, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 664)
        Apparent arrival at the Havana airport of Fidel Castro, greeted by press agents (frame 8). Unidentified American man, possibly a U.S. official, wearing a business suit, appears in profile in Frame 9. Bottom images show tourists cavorting poolside at the Hotel Presidente in el Vedado, Havana. See also Prints 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, and 16.
      - Book IX Print 18: Raúl Castro, the Chief of Cuba's Fuerzas Armadas Revolucionarias since October 1959 to the present, giving a speech on national television. See also Prints 6 and 8, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 665)
      - Book IX Print 19: Attempted landing of United States Piper Apache aircraft on secret mission to Cuba, 1960 May (Box 7, Folder 666)
        This folder encloses both a contact sheet and an empty envelope for holding negatives with a typed descriptive text. As confirmed by this text, images in the contact sheet show the aborted attempted landing of a U.S.-based Piper Apache aircraft, flown by Matthew Edward Duke, on a secret mission to Cuba in order to facilitate the escape of four former officials of the Batista regime who were probably facing trial and possible execution in Cuba for war crimes. According to St. George's notes typed on envelope enclosed, the crash took place on May 12, 1960.
      - Book IX Print 20: Women's militia, the Unidad Femenina Revolucionaria, on parade; Fidel Castro participating in Ernest Hemingway's fishing tournament, 1960 May (Box 7, Folder 667)
        Frames 10-12 of the second row and images 3-9 of the fourth and fifth rows show an all-female militia called the Unidad Femenina Revolucionaria parading down San Rafael Boulevard in Centro Habana, towards Central Park where a number of citizens are gathered (Frame 12), probably for the commemoration of the anniversary of the death of José Martí on May 19, 1960. All other images show Fidel participating in Ernest Hemingway's famed May 1960 fishing tournament, staged in the Marina Barlovento, now known as the Marina Hemingway in Cuba. Frames 15-19, 20-24 show Fidel Castro on board the fishing vessel, Cristal, returning with his catch. Frames 30-34 show Fidel smiling as his fish are weighed. Later, Fidel would be proclaimed the winner of all the main fishing prizes and trophies given out by Hemingway. See also Prints 21, 22, 23, 24, 25, 26, 27, 41, 63 and 64.
      - Book IX Prints 21-23: Fidel Castro participating in Ernest Hemingway's fishing tournament, 1960 May (Box 7, Folder 668-670)
        Images of Fidel Castro and Ernest Hemingway at the latter's May 1960 fishing tournament, held in Marina Barlovento, now known as Marina Hemingway, outside of Havana. Fidel Castro won all the principal fishing prizes on that day. See also Prints 20, 22, 23, 25, 26, 27, 41, 63 and 64.
      - Book IX Print 24: Parade by pro-government groups and route along San Rafael Boulevard, 1960 May (Box 7, Folder 671)
        Top frames show San Rafael Boulevard, in Centro Habana, parade route for Unidad Femenina Revolucionaria, all-female militia, and other pro-government groups. Parade seems to have culminated in Central Park, before the statue to José Martí, a traditional site for political protests and parades coinciding with national patriotic celebrations. This parade seems to have been in honor of either the birth of the Republic (Cuban Independence Day), May 20th, or more likely, the anniversary of the death of José Martí, May 19. See also Print 20.
      - Book IX Prints 25-26: Fidel Castro participating in Ernest Hemingway's fishing tournament, 1960 May (Box 7, Folder 672-673)
        Images of Fidel Castro and Ernest Hemingway at the latter's May 1960 fishing tournament, held in Marina Barlovento, now known as Marina Hemingway, outside of Havana. Fidel Castro won all the principal fishing prizes on that day. See also Prints 20, 21, 22, 23, 27, 41, 63 and 64.
      - Book IX Print 27: Fidel Castro participating in Ernest Hemingway's fishing tournament, including photographs of Mary Hemingway and unidentified American celebrity, 1960 May (Box 7, Folder 674)
        Fidel Castro shows off the fish captured and trophies he won at Hemingway's fishing tournament in May of 1960 and converses with the host, Ernest Hemingway. Frame 15 of Print 27 also shows Mary Hemingway, standing next to her husband, Ernest Hemingway. Frames 7, 17, 8-12 show Fidel Castro and Hemingway standing next to and talking to an unidentified American celebrity who accompanied Fidel on the Cristal earlier the day of the tournament. See also Prints 20, 21, 22, 23, 24, 25, 26, 41, 63, and 64.
      - Book IX Print 28: Cuban nationalization of American oil businesses, 1960 June (Box 7, Folder 675)
        Images of the Cuban revolutionary government's nationalization of the U.S.-owned oil refinery known as Esso in Cuba (Exxon in the United States), as well as Shell Oil in June 1960. These refineries were located near the Bay of Havana. Their nationalization came as a result of Soviet offers to sell Cuba Russian crude oil at much reduced prices and the U.S. government's refusal to allow its companies to refine the oil. This was the first of all U.S.-owned businesses to be nationalized in the summer of 1960. This process was completed by August and capped off by the imposition of a U.S. embargo against Cuba in October that then prompted the Cubans' subsequent decision to nationalize all properties owned by U.S. citizens, not just businesses. In all, Cuba nationalized hundreds of millions of dollars of U.S. businesses and properties. In frames 3-5 of this print, a cloth banner signed by the "Sección Sindical de [unclear]" denounces Yankee imperialism and claims the fatherland ["patria"] for the Cubans. See also Prints 29, 31, 36, 37, 38, 39, 40, 42, 43 and 44.
      - Book IX Print 29: Members of Cuban military patrol the recently nationalized Shell oil refinery. See also Prints 28, 31, 36, 37, 38, 39, 40, 42, 43 and 44., 1960 June (Box 7, Folder 676)
      - Book IX Print 30: Mid-afternoon traffic on Havana's Malecón; repair of sidewalk in from of the 'Edificio Horman,', 1960 June (Box 7, Folder 677)
        Images of mid-afternoon traffic jam on Havana's Malecón, directly in front of the Parque Maceo and near the Church of the Virgen of Carmen. Frames 26-28 of the second-to-last row depict St. George, the photographer, observing a group of workers repairing a sidewalk in front of the 'Edificio Horman.' See also Print 65.
      - Book IX Print 31: Search of employee cars at Shell Oil, 1960 June (Box 7, Folder 678)
        Images of Shell Oil employees leaving the nationalized refinery and having their cars searched by members of the Cuban revolutionary police while television cameras and reporters record the event. See also Prints 28, 29, 31, 36, 37, 38, 39, 40, 42, 43 and 44.
      - Book IX Print 32: Musical group at La Terraza; miniature car racing; Fidel Castro giving speech, 1960 June (Box 7, Folder 679)
        Top rows of images (frames 3-15) feature backlit photographs of musical group playing at the restaurant and bar La Terraza, in the Plaza of Arms, overlooking Havana harbor and facing the Fortaleza de la Cabaña. Frames 16 and 17 show miniature car racing at a small amusement park on the western end of the Malecón, Havana's sea wall. Bottom frames show Fidel giving an impassioned speech. See also Print 33.
      - Book IX Print 33: Fidel Castro giving speech; hotel without tourists, 1960 June (Box 7, Folder 680)